Mary van Kleeck Papers, 1849-1998
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Mary van Kleeck papers
1883-1972
van Kleeck, Mary
MS 165
126 boxes, 56 volumes (66.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Social reformer, Lecturer, Social researcher, Writer, Social worker. Papers include correspondence, biographical material, clippings, speeches, writings, research notes, subject and organization files, primarily from van Kleeck's professional life. There is a significant amount of material relating to Smith College, her work in social and charitable agencies such as ACLU, National Woman's Party, Bryn Mawr Summer School for Student Workers, Hospites (a refugee rescue organization), the Women's International Democratic Federation, the Women's Trade Union League, and the National Research Council. Also the Russell Sage Foundation's Department of Industrial Studies where she conducted investigations of the Rocky Mountain Fuel Company, United Mine Workers, and the coal industry, and her work with Mary Anderson at the Women's Bureau and Mary Fledderus at the International Industrial Relations Institute, 1925-47.
Mary Abby Van Kleeck was born on June 26, 1883 in Glenham, New York, to Eliza Mayer and Episcopalian minister Robert Boyd Van Kleeck. (Mary van Kleeck changed the capitalization of her last name in the 1920s.) Following her father's death in 1892, her family moved to Flushing, New York, where van Kleeck attended Flushing High School. She entered Smith College in the fall of 1900, became involved in the Smith College Association for Christian Work, and began a lifelong affiliation with the YWCA. Van Kleeck earned an A.B. from Smith College in 1904.
In the fall of 1905 van Kleeck began working as a fellow for the College Settlement Association on Rivington Street on New York's Lower East Side. She worked with several women reformers, attended sociology classes at Columbia, and researched factory women and child labor. Her work with the College Settlement Association, and later as the industrial secretary of the Alliance Employment Bureau, caught the attention of the Russell Sage Foundation. The Foundation began supporting her research, and in 1910, hired her as the head of its Committee on Women's Work. Van Kleeck's pioneering research into the fields of artificial flower-making, millinery, and bookbinding, helped pass legislation limiting night work for female workers and led to an extension of van Kleeck's role at the Russell Sage Foundation. Beginning in 1914, she taught at the New York School of Philanthropy and in the 1920s, at Smith College's School for Social Work. In 1916, the Foundation's Committee of Women's Work expanded to create the Division of Industrial Studies, later renamed Department of Industrial Studies (DIS). Mary van Kleeck was asked to serve as director of the new division, a title she would hold for over forty years, except for a brief period of time during World War I.
As one of the most influential figures in women's employment, van Kleeck joined the Army's Ordinances Department in early 1918, creating standards for the employment of women in war industries. She served on the War Labor Policies Board, and with strong backing from the Women's Trade Union League, she was named the director of the U.S. Department of Labor's Women in Industry Service, the precursor of the U.S. Women's Bureau. Van Kleeck held the position only briefly, before handing it over to the assistant director, Mary Anderson, and returning to the Russell Sage Foundation in New York to care for her dying mother. Although van Kleeck was slated to be the first director of the Women's Bureau, Mary Anderson took over van Kleeck's position before the official creation date of the Women's Bureau, and therefore Anderson became its first director.
After her mother's death, van Kleeck returned to her studies of labor, employment, and industry at the national, state, and local levels. In 1921 Commerce Secretary Herbert Hoover appointed van Kleeck to President Harding's Conference on Unemployment. Following the conference, van Kleeck continued to investigate the causes of unemployment and the means to prevent it as a member of the Standing Committee of the Conference and Sub-Committee on the Business Cycle. In 1922 van Kleeck introduced a uniform method for calculating periodic statistics for employment at the Labor Law Administration Conference held in Milford, Pennsylvania. At the Department of Industrial Studies at the Russell Sage Foundation, Mary van Kleeck expanded her studies of workers' rights and the role of employee representation in the workplace. After a careful examination of John D. Rockefeller's method of employee representation in the Colorado coal mines, reported in Employees' Representation in Coal Mines, a Study of the Industrial Representation Plan of the Colorado Fuel and Iron Company in 1924, van Kleeck concluded that this method of employee-employer relations only partially protected workers. While working and living conditions had improved in the Rockefeller plan, employees still lacked the power to influence many workplace decisions. Van Kleeck believed that when workers participated more actively in the management of the organization, efficiency increased and labor was more productive. In addition to her own research at the Russell Sage Foundation, van Kleeck supervised several significant studies, including those of the Dutchess Bleachery, the Filene Store, the Rock Island Arsenal, and the Rocky Mountain Fuel Company.
Mary van Kleeck continued to fight for the rights of women workers during the 1920s, speaking on the role of women wage earners at both the 1923 and 1926 American Women's Conference on Industrial Problems, sponsored by the Department of Labor's Women's Bureau. The 1926 Conference erupted in controversy when representatives from the National Women's Party protested their exclusion from the conference program. As an advocate of workers' rights, van Kleeck disagreed with champions of women's rights who supported the proposed Equal Rights Amendment, fearing that it would interfere with the special protections she had helped enact for female workers. Van Kleeck and New York Women's Trade Union League member Mabel Leslie sparred with the equal rights legislation supporters in a special session held at the 1926 Conference.
Van Kleeck spent much of her time traveling across the country and even the world, researching, lecturing, and addressing a wide variety of audiences. She served on the Board of Trustees at her alma mater from 1922 to 1930, and worked for Al Smith's campaign for president in 1928. In 1929 van Kleeck accepted an appointment to Hoover's Law Enforcement and Observance Commission to investigate the relationship between unemployment and inadequate housing and crime in urban areas. She also promoted social and economic planning, serving from 1928 to 1948 as associate director of the International Industrial Relations Institute (known as IRI), an organization dedicated to the investigation of industrial relations as well as a place for industry to exchange ideas and improve working conditions for workers. In addition to examining economic policies in the United States, van Kleeck also traveled to Europe and the Soviet Union, spending six weeks exploring labor conditions in the U.S.S.R. in 1932. She supported the Soviets' economic policies of collective ownership and industrial planning and spent much of the next two decades praising Soviet society. In spite of conflicts between the two nations following World War II, van Kleeck remained an advocate of Soviet socialism and encouraged Russian-American co-existence.
Mary van Kleeck fought hard for social insurance legislation during the 1930s. In 1931 she and fellow members of the Taylor Society's Industrial Code Committee advocated a minimum living wage, a shorter work day and week, and unemployment insurance for industry in the United States. Van Kleeck blamed the economic depression on the lack of coordination between supply and demand as well as inadequate care for laborers. She supported the Wagner Employment Bill, which created the United States Employment Service, and worked on a New York state unemployment survey that helped connect the unemployed with businesses needing employees. While van Kleeck worked hard with government officials to bring about legislative remedies to economic problems, she did not hesitate to criticize government policies when she disagreed with them. She resigned from the Labor Department's Federal Advisory Committee of the United States Employment Service in August 1933 after one day, citing her objections to New Deal policies that she believed interfered with workers' right to strike.
In addition to working through government to promote social change, Mary van Kleeck served on the committees and boards of secular and religious humanitarian organizations such as the Church League for Industrial Democracy; the Episcopal League for Social Action; and Hospites, a refugee relocation organization that provided employment and financial assistance for social workers fleeing Nazi Germany in the 1930s. A lifelong Episcopalian, van Kleeck hoped that introducing Christian values into the workplace would solve much of industry's problems. Mary van Kleeck believed that she had a Christian duty to promote social change and that churches and church-based organizations should play a role in remediating struggles of the worker.
Mary van Kleeck remained dedicated to the rights of workers in the mid-to-late 1930s. Concern for workers' liberties led Mary van Kleeck to leadership roles in the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), where she served on the Board of Directors and several committees from 1935 until 1940 when a conflict with the board over membership requirements prompted her to resign. A big supporter of trade unions, strikes and labor parties, she participated in a variety of ACLU activities, including opposing oaths of allegiance by schoolteachers in the mid 1930s. In 1934 van Kleeck continued her pursue her interest in the status of mine workers, publishing Miners and Management: A Study of the Collective Agreement between the United Mine Workers of America and the Rocky Mountain Fuel Company. Van Kleeck registered with the American Labor Party in 1936, impressed by its commitment to the protection of civil liberties and advocacy of social and economic planning. That same year, van Kleeck published Creative America: Its Resources for Social Security, a treatise emphasizing the need for socio-economic planning in the U.S. In 1939 she fought the deportation of Frank Borisch, secretary of the National Miners' Union who was convicted of belonging to an organization that advocated the overthrow of the government.
Mary van Kleeck opposed the United States' entry into World War II, believing that the conflict was an imperialist endeavor. Once it became clear that the United States would participate, however, van Kleeck urged women's participation at all levels of government administration. She also advocated an expansion of the social security program. She believed that post-war peace plans must include a worldwide defense of human rights. Mary van Kleeck spent the rest of the decade encouraging community organization, nuclear disarmament, and the peacetime use of atomic energy. In 1944 she co-authored with Mary F. Fleddérus, Technology and Livelihood, a report of the effect of technological innovations on employment and standards of living from World War I to the early 1940s. In this report, van Kleeck maintained that innovation did not always improve one's livelihood; in fact, increased efficiency often increased unemployment or underemployment. Therefore, she supported unions and welfare funds as a necessity to gain and maintain decent standards of living for workers.
In 1948, after her retirement, she supported Henry A. Wallace's campaign for president and unsuccessfully ran for the New York State Senate as the American Labor Party candidate. Because of her interactions with various organizations that had been declared subversive by the Attorney General Herbert Brownell, Jr., she was subpoenaed by Joseph McCarthy's Senate Permanent Subcommittee on Investigations of the Committee on Government Operations in 1953 and was denied a visa several times in the 1950s. Mary van Kleeck spent the last few decades of her life out of the public sphere with her close friend and colleague, Mary L. Fleddérus. Mary van Kleeck died on June 8, 1972, in Kingston, New York, of heart failure while undergoing surgery for a broken hip.
The Mary van Kleeck Papers consist of nearly sixty-seven linear feet of material, dating from 1849 to 1998, and are primarily related to her professional and public life. Types of material include biographical information and memorabilia, correspondence, speeches, writings, lectures, photographs, research notes, memoranda, reports, journal and newspaper articles, as well as organization and subject files.
These papers are primarily composed of documents and materials produced by the professional and public activities of Mary van Kleeck, the bulk of which span the years from 1917 to 1960. They include relatively little about her personal life. She spent several years organizing her papers, and the lack of biographical material was a deliberate choice. Most of the biographical materials that are included in the collection have come from other sources-family members of van Kleeck and Mary L. Fleddérus, researchers (especially Guy Alchon), and the federal government through Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests made by Eleanor M. Lewis of the Sophia Smith Collection and researcher Guy Alchon.
Mary van Kleeck was involved in a wide variety of social, political and economic studies and organizations over the course of her lifetime, and she saved much of the correspondence, business, research, and printed materials related to her interests. The papers offer a rich cache of information about a variety of subjects, people, and organizations in the first half of the twentieth century, especially radical/left groups, from the international to local level. Her work at the Russell Sage Foundation and the International Industrial Relations Institute (IRI) compose the largest portions of the organizational records. The internal workings of the Department of Industrial Studies of the Russell Sage Foundation, as well as the businesses and subjects van Kleeck researched there, are well-documented within this collection, especially those companies that formed the basis of the Foundation's landmark studies, such as Colorado Fuel and Iron Company, Dutchess Bleachery, Filene Store, Rock Island Arsenal, and the Rocky Mountain Fuel Company. There is a wealth of information in the background research, field notes, correspondence, drafts, and final versions of the Russell Sage Foundation studies. Other subject areas are well-covered in the Foundation records, including the hundreds of businesses studied regarding employee representation in the workplace and the effect of the National Recovery Administration on industry. The records of the International Industrial Relations Institute include detailed notes, correspondence, subject files, speeches and debates from the many conferences and congresses that the organization held during van Kleeck's tenure, as well as materials related to the administration and publications of the IRI.
Mary van Kleeck served on numerous boards and special committees, including the American Association of Social Workers, American Association of University Women, American Civil Liberties Union, National Woman's Party, Bryn Mawr Summer School for Student Workers, International Labor Office of the League of Nations, and the National Research Council. The collection documents this work thoroughly. There is a significant amount of material relating to Smith College, both during the years she spent as a student and her later service to the institution. Other groups that are well-represented in the collection include the Young Women's Christian Association, the Women's Trade Union League, and Taylor Society. Of particular interest is her work with Mary Anderson at the Women's Bureau in the Department of Labor, and with Mary Fleddérus at the International Industrial Relations Institute.
In addition to organizational records, van Kleeck kept subject files on a wide variety of topics, especially U.S and international labor, protective legislation, trade unions, employer- employee relations, social research, social welfare, social work and social security, and the coal industry. Other major subjects addressed throughout the collection include race relations, Christian socialism, peace, women's rights and the Equal Rights Amendment, social settlements, New Deal legislation and policies, the social and economic organization of the Soviet Union, unemployment, and employment during World War I and World War II.
Significant correspondents include Mary Anderson, Susan B. Anthony II, Mary Beard, Elizabeth Christman, Eleanor Coit, Dorothy Douglas, Mary Fleddérus, Pauline Goldmark, Margaret Grierson, Alice Hamilton, John L. Lewis, Mabel Leslie, William Allan Neilson, Gifford Pinchot, Frances Perkins, Eleanor and Franklin D. Roosevelt, Rose Schneiderman, Florence Simms, William Spofford, M. Carey Thomas, Lillian Wald, and Max Yergan.
This collection is organized as follows:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. CORRESPONDENCE
III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
IV. SUBJECT FILES, 1905-1960
V. ORGANIZATION AND CONFERENCE FILES
VI. BOOKS FROM VAN KLEECK'S LIBRARY
VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Mary van Kleeck donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1956 to 1972. Small additions came later from Barbara Stevens Roberts, Terry Brown, Guy Alchon, J. Dyck Fledderus, and Ruth S. Lenonard. In 2004, Guy Alchon donated a large cache of materials that included his research files, oral histories with family and friends of van Kleeck, and personal correspondence between Mary van Kleeck and family as well as childhood and collegiate friends.
Search Terms
American Association of Social Workers--History--Sources; American Association of University Women--History--Sources; American Civil Liberties Union--History--Sources; Bryn Mawr College. Summer School for Women Workers in Industry; Civil rights--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Coal industry and trade--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Coal miners--United States--History--Sources; Cost and standard of living--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Equal rights amendments--United States--History--Sources; Female friendship--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Industrial hygiene--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Industrial relations--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Insurance, Unemployment--Law and legislation--United States--History--Sources; International Industrial Relations Institute--History--Sources; Labor laws and legislation--United States--History--Sources; Labor--Research--United States; Labor--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Management--Employee participation--United States--History--Sources; National Research Council (U.S.)--History--Sources; National Woman's Party--History--Sources; National Women's Trade Union League of America--History--Sources; New Deal, 1933-1939; Refugees, Jewish--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Rocky Mountain Fuel Company; Russell Sage Foundation--History--Sources; Smith College. School for Social Work--History--Sources; Social reformers--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Social settlements--New York (N.Y.)--History--Sources; Social work administration--United States--History--Sources; Socialism, Christian--United States--History--Sources; Soviet Union--Economic conditions--1917-1945; Unemployment--History--Sources; United Mine Workers of America--History--20th century--Sources; United States. Women's Bureau--History--Sources; Women--Congresses--History; Women--Economic conditions--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Employment--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Legal status, laws, etc.--History--20th century--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--Women--United States; World War, 1939-1945--Women--United States; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--History; Anderson, Mary; Beard, Mary Ritter, 1876-1958--Correspondence; Coit, Eleanor G.--Correspondence; Douglas, Dorothy W. (Dorothy Wolff), 1890-1968--Correspondence; Fledderus, Mary L. (Mary Lambertine), 1886- --Correspondence; Goldmark, Pauline Dorothea--Correspondence; Grierson, Margaret--Correspondence; Hamilton, Alice, 1869-1970--Correspondence; Leslie, Mabel--Correspondence; Lewis, John Llewellyn, 1880-1969--Correspondence; Neilson, William Allan, 1869-1946--Correspondence; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945--Correspondence; Schneiderman, Rose, 1882- --Correspondence; Simms, Florence, 1873-1923; Thomas, M. Carey (Martha Carey), 1857-1935--Correspondence; Van Kleeck, Mary, 1883-; Wald, Lillian D., 1867-1940--Correspondence; Yergan, Max--Correspondence
Additional Information
Related Material
Van Kleeck sent some papers related to labor research to the Archives of Labor History and Urban Affairs at Wayne State University. Additional papers of Mary van Kleeck are located at the National Archives, Social and Industrial Branch, in the records of the Department of Labor, Women in Industry Service, Women's Bureau, and War Labor Policies Board.
There is additional material about van Kleeck in the Smith College Archives and many of her published works are available in the Five College Libraries.
Collections in the Sophia Smith Collection with related subject matter include the Employment Collection, the League of Women Shoppers, the Young Women's Christian Association, and the American Association of University Women. The papers of Vida Dutton Scudder include additional materials on College Settlement Work, the Church League for Industrial Democracy, and the Women's Trade Union League. Correspondence from Mary van Kleeck to Ethel Clyde is located in the Biography Collection.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS1878-1985, 9 linear ft.
  This series focuses on biographical information about Mary van Kleeck and includes the following subseries about her life: Personal history, Education, Daily activities, and material gathered from the federal government through a FOIA (Freedom of Information Act) request. Photographs include prints, proofs, uncut rolls of negatives and glass slides taken by Mary van Kleeck as well as many pictures of van Kleeck and her family taken by others. The subseries, Daily activities, includes a list of her activities between 1930 and 1931, written on notecards as well as more traditional diary-like entries of her time with the College Settlement Association in 1905 and of her six weeks in the Soviet Union in 1932. The subseries, Education, includes material from her time at Smith and her relationship with the institution as an alumna, as well as class notes from other schools that she attended. Articles and newspaper clippings are found within this series, as are Papers, theses, and dissertations. Biographical information about her Family and friends is a subseries as well. The subseries Related collections include photocopies from other collections, most of which were compiled by Guy Alchon in his research on Mary van Kleeck. Permission to use copies of materials from other institutions must be sought from those institutions.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE1849-1981, 5.75 linear ft.